It's early.
Next is a mac security mechanism used in Android.
So MAC stands for mandatory access control.
So to understand Linux well, we need to know what Mac and DAC are.
So MAC stands for mandatory access control and DAC stands for Discretionary Access Control.
Mac and DAC are two of the most popular access control models in use.
The main difference between them is in how they provide access to the users.
So in mandatory access control or MAC, the system determines which subjects can access specific data
objects in discretionary access control or DAC.
The owner of the object, the owner of the object specifies which subjects can access the object.
So this is typical case.
In Linux, AC Linux is a mac security mechanism to make it very simple.
Let's try to understand this with an example.
Imagine that you own a farm house and you have cows, rabbits and chickens.
Each animal in the farmhouse should eat specific food.
None of these animals or birds would not eat each other's food.
Let's imagine that you have a robot who will take care of this farmhouse.
The robot will look after the animals and make sure that they eat the right food based on your instruction.
So you have to instruct the robot with some rules.
So you need to say, a cow should only eat grass.
Rabbit should only eat carrots.
Chicken should only eat chicken food.
So when you write these rules in silliness, you will write something like this.
Allow cows.
Grass and food.
Eat.
Allow rabbit.
Carrot.
Call and food.
Eat.
Allow.
Chicken.
Grains.
Colon.
Food.
Eat.
So this is a typical SELinux policy rule, as we can see.
A select policy rule comes in this form.
The first one is the keyword which says Allow.
Second one is the source.
So this is the type of the subject of the rule.
So this is basically the subject.
In our first example, the subject is cow.
Right?
So this is basically who is requesting the access and then comes the archetype of the object.
What is the access requested?
So in the first example, cow is requesting grass.
So the cow is requesting access to the grass.
And the third part is the class, the kind of object being accessed.
So in our example it is the food, and then the last one is the permissions.
So in our example, the cow is requesting the permission to eat the food, right?
So this is a typical SC policy rule.
Okay, now let's look at the subjects and objects in Android so we can replace cows, rabbits and chickens
with processors or process types in Android, and we can replace grass added and grains with files,
socket, other processors, etc. in Android.
So a real world example will look something like this.
Allow untrusted app app data file colon file read right and the kernel will look at these rules and
make sure that the subjects follows it.
So in this a policy rule which we have seen where allowing untrusted apps access to apps data file so
it can read or write.
So all untrusted apps could read or write app data file.
So files that end with starter D are the SC Linux policy source files where we write the SELinux rules.
So in this example App Store, we can find one rule it says Allow app domain mine process hal file file
class read permission and also it's a good no trends permission.
So in this case we are allowing the process which comes under the app domain access to this particular
file that read and execute not trans permissions.
Similarly, you can find many other files.
So file here we are declaring some types.
We look at types in a later session.
So here in context 30, you can find many other rules.
So all the rules will be basically under the files with standard extension.
There are many other files, other supporting files for these rules.
So for example, Jen FS underscore context and file underscore context.
These files basically defines the names or classes or domains of different resources within the system.
We'll have a look at these in detail in the later tutorials.
For now, just keep in mind that starter D files consist of all the.
See the next rules and you can find all the AC policies of a particular hardware or a board.
Under this path, under the device folder, you will get the manufacturer name like Amlogic, Google,
Linear or MediaTek D Board.
So if we take Leonardo as an example, we come inside that you can see different devices, the Dragon
board, AI keyboard and under the board name or the device name, you can find a folder with the name
Z Policy.
Here we have the AC policy here and under the AC policy will have all the start e files where we define
the AC policies and its supporting files where we declare the domain types extra.